Guide to the Benjamin and Julia Stockton Rush Papers, 1766-1845 and undated RL.11044
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Letters, 1777-1824; 1
  - Rush, Benjamin (n.p.) letter to [John Bubenheim Bayard], 1784 June 25; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 2 Leaves; 3 pages; 34 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    A copy, in an unknown hand, of a letter from Rush to Bayard regarding sentiments expressed in an earlier letter to General John Armstrong. The letter reflects post-revolutionary state politics in Pennsylvania. In the letter, Rush censures his fellow Presbyterians, who refuse to revoke the test laws and to admit amendments to the state constitution. He also condemns the taking over by the Presbyterian dominated state government of the charter of the College of Philadelphia, now the University of Pennsylvania, and refers to the College of Carlisle, or Dickinson College, established in protest to the first action. He regrets the inflammatory remarks and publications made by members of the state's single legislative body, the Council of Censors, and by Joseph Reed and Mr. Smiley, and deplores the character of Henry Osborn and Owen Faris.
    Pennsylvania -- History -- 18th century; Bayard, John Bubenheim, 1738-1807; Armstrong, John, 1758-1843; University of Pennsylvania; Dickinson College
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1786 August 23; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rush writes that he expects their friend, Dr. Hall, to marry soon. He also writes of his activities with his boys. More particularly, his son John accompanied him on rounds at the hospital and showed no emotion while witnessing an operation. Rush also described in detail their visit to a mentally disturbed patient. He is pleased that John has expressed a desire to become a physician.
    Rush, Julia Stockton; Rush family
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1787 August 16; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 32 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rush writes about solitude, and how he misses having his wife and family to impart his thoughts and ideas to immediately.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1787 August 22; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rush writes that he wishes to share his reading of Paley's moral philosophy with her, because he would enjoy it more that way and it would better qualify her to educate their children. He describes a gathering where he provided beer to a group of laborers, and how affectionate one of them was to his dog, including a reflection of "infinite love which follows the human species." He then comments that their leaving a local congregation has finally been noticed. The signature line for this letter has been excised.
    Books and reading -- United States -- History -- 18th century; Women -- Education -- United States; Rush, Julia Stockton; Paley, William, 1743-1805 -- Principles of moral and political philosophy; Rush family
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Rev [Ashbel?] Green (n. p.), 1787 September 19; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 24 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rush explains his reasons for leaving the Reverend's church; he mentions Rev. Sproat.
    Sproat, James, 1722-1793; Rush family
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to George Clymer (n. p.), 1789 February 12; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rush outlines a full course of treatment for an undefined equine disease, including bloodletting.
    Horses -- Diseases -- Early works to 1800; Horses -- Diseases -- Treatment; Clymer, George, 1739-1813
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1791 July 16-17; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 32 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rush writes of their exchange of letters, and mentions both of their sons, along with the grandson of President Washington, who is ill with a fever and is being attended by doctors Shippen and Kuhn. He also successfully treats a woman with a locked jaw. He announces his plan to open an African Church, and describes the resulting excitement in the free black community.
    Trismus; Rush, Julia Stockton; Shippen, William, 1712-1801; St. Thomas' Church (Philadelphia, Pa.) -- History
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1791 July 29; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 32 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rush takes Julia to task for permitting their son John to have a gun against his expressed wishes. Rush believes John's character is not the correct one for gun ownership, because he lacks gentleness and compassion. Rush requests that Julia not override his dissent, and strengthen their parenting as a result. He announces that he has taken their son Richard to see patients. He is reading John Newton's Cardiphonia. He also is planning to develop a cure for the consumptive cough.
    Firearms ownership -- United States -- 18th century; Books and reading -- United States -- History -- 18th century; Cough; Rush, Julia Stockton; Newton, John, 1725-1807 -- Cardiphonia; Rush family
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1791 August 24; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 32 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rush explains his plans for travel to Princeton, and the minor ailments he has been suffering. He then describes how he visited a patient who was having a fit of colic, only find she was actually in labor. He expects the affair to give him some trouble, but has neither the constitution nor time to practice midwifery. He rejoices in hearing of the fall of the French monarchy, and expects that it will lead to the removal of all the kings in Europe. A later note was added stating that the letter's signature was given to an autograph seeker.
    France -- History -- Revolution, 1789-1799 -- Influence; Childbirth -- United States -- History -- 18th Century; Midwives -- United States -- History -- 18th Century; Rush, Julia Stockton
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Richard Rush (Princeton [N.J.]}, 1792 May 17; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rush writes to his son regarding his education. He expects him to study Latin and arithmetic, and stresses that he needs to pay more attention to his spelling.
    Children -- United States -- History -- 18th Century; Education -- United States -- History -- 18th Century; Rush family
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to James Thornton (n. p.), 1792 September 3; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rush writes to Thornton regarding his opposition to capital punishment, and encloses copies of a his pamphlet on the matter, of which Thronton had approved. Rush also discusses his birthplace, Byberry, where Thornton resides.
    Byberry (Philadelphia, Pa.) -- History; Capital punishment -- United States -- History; Thornton, James, 1727-1794
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 August 21; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush announces that a violent "fever" has broken out in one district of the city, where 12 people have died. If it spreads he plans to have Julia remain at Princeton. He then reports that influenza continues to spread, with violent symptoms that cause him anxiety. He adds that Mr. Wolstonecraft has refused to purchase their property, because he could not support himself by hunting on it. Finally, he notes the arrival of a fellow physician's son from France, who brings disturbing news of the state of affairs, there.
    Yellow fever -- 18th century; Yellow Fever -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Yellow Fever -- Epidemiology -- Pennsylvania; Rush, Julia Stockton
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Trenton [N.J.]), 1793 August 25-26; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 32 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush updates Julia on the alarming spread of the fever. He reports that the College of Physicians has met to consult on how to stop the spread of disease and to draw up instructions for that purpose. These directions will be handed to the mayor. He asks her to stay in New Jersey with the children, and to pray for his protection, although he takes all precautions possible. He plans to confine his boys to the house for their protection.
    Yellow fever -- 18th century; Yellow Fever -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Yellow Fever -- Epidemiology -- Pennsylvania; Rush, Julia Stockton; Rush family
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Trenton [N.J.]), 1793 August 26-27; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 32 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush states that the boys are so apprehensive about contracting the fever from his clothes that he has decided to send them to Trenton. He asks her to have them read something useful, because he is worried about possible habits of idleness. He notes that the directions from the College of Physicians are to be published tomorrow, but worries that the fever will not subside before October's heavy rains and frost. His postscript provides instructions on how to protect the boys.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Trenton [N.J.]), 1793 August 27; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush notes that both boys have headaches, but are travelling regardless. He reports on the fever in their neighborhood, listing who has died or left town.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Trenton [N.J.]), 1793 August 29-30; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 32 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush provides a detailed account of the yellow fever epidemic, describing its varied presentation among individuals. He notes that the violence of the fever has caused Philadelphians to mistake it for plague. He points out that common remedies have all failed, but he consults with Dr. Caspar Wistar regarding treatments.
    Yellow fever -- 18th century; Yellow Fever -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Yellow Fever -- Epidemiology -- Pennsylvania; Yellow fever -- Treatment; Yellow Fever -- therapy; Rush, Julia Stockton
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Trenton [N.J.]), 1793 September 1-2; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 32 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    3-page transcript available
    Rush describes the funerals taking place in the city, and tells Julia that the fever has been particularly fatal to the young. He rejoices that the boys left the city, but hopes they avoid fatigue, heat, and cold, so that they do not excite any portion of the fever they might have carried with them from town. He expresses concern that the city is only at the beginning of the epidemic, but joins Julia in planning to express more gratitude for God's mercies in the future.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 3; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush records that his case load is increasing, as is his fatigue, but that many of those he treats are out of danger. He reports on the progress of the epidemic in their neighborhood.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Trenton [N.J.]), 1793 September 4; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush briefly notes that the disease spreads, but mortality is not in proportion to the numbers afflicted. His cure is jalap and mercury, taken on the first day of the attack.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 5; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 2 Leaves; 3 pages; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush writes that he has seen 100 patients, and that he now saves almost all those he sees within the first day. He notes that some doctors rail against the cure he uses, several of them publishing false information, even though they generally have not visited patients with the fever. He chronicles the fate of several doctors that have contracted the disease. He notes that some of his friends are ashamed to see him once they fall ill. He admonishes her once more to watch the boys closely for signs of infection, for the fever will lie dormant 1 to 16 days following contraction.
    Yellow fever -- 18th century; Yellow Fever -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Yellow Fever -- Epidemiology -- Pennsylvania; Yellow fever -- Treatment; Yellow Fever -- therapy; Rush, Julia Stockton; Rush family
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 6-7; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush notes that his cure is working, but there is a pause in new cases, and that fatalities are now among the poor without access to doctors or respectable people being treated by quacks. He states that if the fever breaks out in Princeton, he will send his assistant John Cox to execute his cure. Once again he documents the health status of his fellow physicians, although he records a rumor that some doctors have ceased seeing patients at all. He then discusses the various treatments that have been used for the fever. In a postscript, he adds that Africans in the city have proven immune to the disease.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 8; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush tells Julia that the pause is over; he has been called to countless cases. Two more doctors are ill, Dr. Morris has died, and Secretary Hamilton is sick. He describes the support he receives from friends, along with the more serious symptoms of the fever.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 10; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush expresses amazement that he remains uninfected by the fever, for he has seen over 100 patients on this date, and 40 people were buried. He states that he does not forget to treat the poor "remembering my dream in the Autumn of 1780." Many doctors have adopted his treatment, but several oppose it, as they oppose his treatment for lockjaw. He remarks that more of the French exiles have come down with the fever. He is now using bloodletting as a tool, since the weather is cooler.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 11; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush notes that the efficacy of his cures is now proven, and that his directions for treating and preventing the disease will be published in the newspapers. He adds that he is in surprisingly good health, since his meals now consist only of milk and vegetables, and water.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 12; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush writes that he is preparing for the "awful duties of the day," as yesterday exceeded any of the preceding days in distress and death, and two more physicians are ill.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 13; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush notes that the fever has been said to become more mild, but that is not the case, especially if his treatment has not been used. He adds that besides combatting the fever, he has to contend with the "prejudices, fears, & falsehoods" of his fellow physicians. He adds that all are tinged with infection, now. Even his own eyes are tinged a yellow color.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 15; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 34 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush refers to the tremendous opposition fellow physicians have given him regarding his cures, and Dr. Kuhn's publications have done the most harm. Rush announces that he has used his methods to cure his own attack of the fever.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 17; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush states that he is sending his assistants out to his patients, and will now visit the most serious cases. He updates her on those in the neighborhood who have not survived.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 18; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 24 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush seeks to reassure his wife that he is fully recovered and well cared for. He notes the numbers of those who oppose his treatments that have now left the city. He adds that it is cold, and that he hopes this will check the fever.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 18; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 2 Leaves; 7 pages; 24 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush describes how he has been forced to limit the number of patients he sees, and the reactions of those whose treatment he declines. He also describes how many of those who become infected are abandoned. He mentions that there is fear of famine in the city.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 20; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 24 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush says that distress increases in Philadelphia, and names several friends and one doctor who have died.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 21; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 24 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush announces that he is well, but has a sore throat from his treatment. He saw 25 patients by carriage; then 25 more, mostly poor people, at home, but was still forced to turn away 38 others. Their house continues as a hospital. He says that his professional detractors are increasing their persecution of him.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 22-23; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 24 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush enumerates the close family friends that are ill or have died, and notes that only one doctor who continues to follow his treatment.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 23-24; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush announces that his pupil, Johnny Stall, has died. He mentions that citizens universally exhibit symptoms of the fever, but that the poor suffer the most. He hopes the weather will change.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 24; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush announces that another of his assistants, Alston, has died. He admits to extreme weakness, but otherwise is in good health. He points out that bleeders, doctors, apothecaries, and nurses are becoming scarce, as are the medical necessities used to treat the fever.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 25-26; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 32 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush says he has been spending time treating and putting up medicines for the poor. He hopes rain and frost will follow to weaken the contagion. He points out that many have died because they mistake their symptoms for a common fever. He notes that now even the African Americans are succumbing in large numbers.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 26-27; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 32 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush announces that his final apprentice, John Coxe, has died and that his sister is very ill. There is some rain in the city. He reports that Dr. Wistar has published an account of his recovery that is calculated to undermine Rush's treatments.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 29-30; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush reports that his sister is in grave danger and that, by popular demand, physicians have been forced to adopt his treatment for the fever.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 September 30 - October 1; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rush defends his taking in Johnny Stall and Ed Fisher, as neither had any other home. His sister, who was at the brink of death, is better, but his mother is now ill and is refusing treatment.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 1-2; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 33 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush provides a detailed account of his sister's death, describing also the invaluable support she provided to him. He notes that there is a want of cash in the city, and that provisions are costly, and prices high. He adds that many of the committee men who sought to help the poor have now died. He hopes for a change in the weather. The close of the letter is missing.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 2-3; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 33 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush points out that Julia's letters are now delayed at the Post Office by 2 or 3 days, but her recent letter brought him comfort. He says that he cannot think of the family or the children, but lives in the moment, making himself useful to others. His sister has been buried, and he plans to plant medicinal plants at her grave; his mother is fully recovered.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 3-4; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 33 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush states that he receives many inquiries each day from country practitioners, and there is a high cost personally and in postage to answering each letter, so he is publishing an account of the fever, including preventatives and remedies. He reports that he is seeing 40-50 patients a day, and notes the progress in the cases.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 4-5; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 33 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush reports that he has had a relapse of the fever, but is still seeing patients as he can. He adds that the poor, children, and servants have been hardest hit by the fever. Nursing wages are now $4 a day. The signature for the letter has been excised.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 6-7; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 33 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush asks that Julia and the children mourn his sister's death, as he is doing. He is unable to see patients because of continued weakness.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 7-8; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 33 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush announces that the publication about the fever has been well received by the citizens. He updates Julia on the condition of several patients.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 8-9; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 24 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)